Guide to the Reuben Dean Bowen Papers, 1871-1938 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Reuben Dean Bowen papers 1871-1938 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Bowen, Reuben Dean
35.6 Linear Feet 26,683 Items
Businessman, farmer, promoter of the cotton industry, from Paris (Lamar County), Texas.
Chiefly Bowen's business papers, consisting of correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, and printed material and volumes. A major portion of the collection concerns agriculture, especially cotton, including the marketing and promotion of cotton and Bowen's relationship with a number of local and national agricultural organizations. Also includes information about J. P. Morgan and the formation of U.S. Steel Corp., labor and labor legislation, U.S. politics and government, European affairs after World War I, prohibition, and food and drug legislation. The collection also contains the diaries of Adelaide Marie Bowen, Reuben's daughter, from 1918-1921.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Reuben Dean Bowen Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1938.
Collection Overview
The papers of Reuben Dean Bowen span the years 1871-1938 and chiefly are made up of Bowen's business papers, consisting of correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, and printed material and volumes. A major portion of the collection concerns agriculture, especially cotton, including the marketing and promotion of cotton and Bowen's relationship with a number of local and national agricultural organizations. Also includes information about J. P. Morgan and the formation of U.S. Steel Corp., labor and labor legislation, U.S. politics and government, European affairs after World War I, prohibition, and food and drug legislation. The collection also contains the diaries of Adelaide Marie Bowen, Reuben's daughter, from 1918-1921.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Bowen, Adelaide Marie, b. 1896
Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913
United States Steel Corporation
Cotton -- Marketing -- United States
Agriculture -- Texas
World War, 1914-1918
Prohibition
Food law and legislation -- United States
Labor laws and legislation -- United States
Agriculture --Societies, etc.
United States -- Economic conditions -- 1865-1918
United States -- Politics and government
Texas -- Lamar County -- Paris
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1857-1938 and undated, (32 boxes)
  - 1857-1915 Feb. 15 (Box 1)
  - 1915 Feb. 16- Sept. 15 (Box 2)
  - 1915 Sept. 16- Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1916 Jan.- Apr. 15 (Box 4)
  - 1916 Apr. 16- June 15 (Box 5)
  - 1916 June 16- Sept. 20 (Box 6)
  - 1916 Sept. 21- 1917 Apr. 15 (Box 7)
  - 1917 Apr. 16- 1918 Jan. (Box 8)
  - 1918 Feb.- 1919 July (Box 9)
  - 1919 Aug.- 1920 May (Box 10)
  - 1920 June- 1921 Aug. (Box 11)
  - 1921 Sept.- 1922 Aug. (Box 12)
  - 1922 Sept.- 1923 (Box 13)
  - 1924 Jan.- Mar. (Box 14)
  - 1924 Apr.- Dec. (Box 15)
  - 1925 Jan.- Sept. (Box 16)
  - 1925 Oct.- 1926 (Box 17)
  - 1927- 1928 Jan. (Box 18)
  - 1928 Feb.- Aug. (Box 19)
  - 1928 Sept.- 1929 Feb. (Box 20)
  - 1929 Mar.- July (Box 21)
  - 1929 Aug.- Nov. 15 (Box 22)
  - 1929 Nov. 16- 1930 May (Box 23)
  - 1930 June- 1931 Feb. (Box 24)
  - 1931 Mar.- 1932 May (Box 25)
  - 1932 June- 1933 (Box 26)
  - 1934-1938 (Box 27)
  - Undated (Box 28-32)
- Printed Material Series, (10 boxes)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 32-34)
  - Cancelled Checks (Box 35)
  - Christmas Cards and Miscellaneous Cards
  - Pamphlets and Miscellaneous Printed Material (Box 36-37)
  - Pamphlets and Volumes (Box 38-40)
  - Photographs (Box 41)
- Manuscript Volumes Series
  - Bowen, Adelaide Marie. Baby book, 1896-. Paris, TX. Originally M-377. (Box 42)
  - Bowen, Adelaide Marie. Diary, 1918. Paris, TX, and New Orleans, LA. Originally S-378. (Box 42)
  - Bowen, Adelaide Marie. Diary, 1919. Paris, TX, and New Orleans, LA. Originally S-379. (Box 42)
  - Bowen, Adelaide Marie. Diary, 1920. Paris, TX, and New Orleans, LA. Originally S-380. (Box 42)
  - Bowen, Adelaide Marie. Diary, 1921. Paris, TX, and New Orleans, LA. Originally S-381. (Box 42)
  - Cotton Trade Journal, 1938. (Box 42)